Guide to the Yehudi Menuhin Collection ARS-0040
Archive of Recorded Sound
Yehudi Menuhin Collection
1938-1950
ARS-0040
Menuhin, Yehudi, 1916-1999
1.1 linear feet, 2 boxes
Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University Libraries Stanford, California 94305-3076
The collection contains primarily sound recordings of performances of Yehudi Menuhin as violin soloist, with piano accompaniment by Hephzibah Menuhin, or with orchestral accompaniment. Most of the recordings are test pressings made between 1938 and 1950. The first box also contains one folder with three record labels that were removed from three Menuhin discs which are not included in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for research. Listening appointments may require 24 hours notice. Contact the Archive Operations Manager.
Biographical/Historical note
Yehudi Menuhin, an American violinist, conductor, and teacher of Russian descent, was born in New York on April 22, 1916. His early violin studies were with Sigmund Anker and Louis Persinger, and he completed his training with Adolf Busch and George Enescu. As a child prodigy, he gave his earliest professional concerts in San Francisco in 1924 and followed those performances with highly successful debut concerts in New York, Paris, Berlin and London. As a prolific recording artist, Menuhin became known for his performances of Edward Elgar's Violin Concerto, which he recorded in 1932 with the composer conducting. His interest in new music produced more than 40 commissions from such noted composers as Béla Bartók (Sonata for Solo Violin) and William Walton (Sonata for Violin and Piano). Menuhin also championed lesser known works of the past such as Mendelssohn's early Concerto in D Minor and Robert Schumann's Violin Concerto. During the Second World War Menuhin gave more than 500 concerts, and in 1945 he was the first Jewish musical artist to perform in Berlin with the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra, conducted by Wilhelm Furtwängler. In the late 1940s Menuhin became more active as a conductor and teacher. In 1959 he founded the Bath Festival Orchestra, and in 1963 he founded the Menuhin Music School, both in the U.K. As a teacher, he also published books on violin playing and wrote an autobiography. Menuhin remained an active performer throughout his life and died in Berlin on March 12, 1999 during a concert tour of Germany.
Scope and Contents note
This collection of sound recordings was assembled by the family of Yehudi Menuhin. The recordings are primarily 10" and 12" 78 rpm sound discs, including test pressings for various companies such as Victor and The Gramophone Company, from recording sessions that took place between 1938 and 1950. The collection is divided into two sections: (1) 6 10" double-sided discs, with an additional folder containing 3 miscellaneous record labels that were removed from Menuhin discs which are not included in this collection; (2) 33 single-sided and 13 double-sided 12" 78 rpm test pressings + 1 commercially released 12" 33 1/3 rpm long playing disc.
Arrangement note
The collection consists primarily of sound discs and is arranged in two boxes, first by disc size, then alphabetically by composer name. Discs with works for which no composer has been identified are filed alphabetically by title in each box. (1) 10" 78 rpm sound discs + 1 folder of miscellaneous record labels. (2) 12" 78 rpm sound discs, + 1 LP (33 1/3 rpm) sound disc.
Indexing Terms
Baller, Adolph; Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827; Boskovich, Alexander Uriyah, 1907-1964; Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897; Enesco, Georges, 1881-1955; Fershko, Shmuel; Fogel, Y.; Kreisler, Fritz, 1875-1962; Lalo, Edouard, 1823-1892; Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847; Menuhin, Hephzibah, 1920-1981; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791; Nissimov, Nissim; Orchestre de l'association des concerts Colonne.; Paganini, Nicolò, 1782-1840; Pizzetti, Ildebrando, 1880-1968; Saidenberg, Theodore; Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828; Solovieff, Miriam; Swoboda, Henry; Weiner, M.; Wiener Staatsoper. Orchester.; Wieniawski, Henri, 1835-1880; Concertos (Violin); Sonatas (Violin and piano); Violin and piano music; Violin music; Violin with orchestra; Violinists--United States
Container List
- 10" sound discs and miscellaneous labels, 7.0 folders (Box 1)
  General note
  Folders 2-7 contain 10" 78 rpm sound recordings.
  - Menuhin labels from 78 rpm 10" discs:, 06-02-1948; 1.0 folder; 3 paper record labels. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    (1) Friendship bridge, performed by Yehudi Menuhin, 3/21/42, #7 of 8. (2) Bruch Concerto (conclusion), performed by Yehudi Menuhin, 6-3-52, Pt. VII of 4-3-52. (3) Paganini Concerto (conclusion), performed by Yehudi Menuhin, 6-3-1952, Part VII of 28-2-52.
  - Boskovich, Alexander Uriyah, 1907-1964: Horra Agadati, arr. by Shmuel Fershko - Popper: The cedars, (Arazim), arr. by Shmuel Fershko., 06-02-1948; 10" vinyl 78 rpm sound disc; Copyright by Tslil Co., Tel Aviv. June 2, 1948 (dub) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Paul Holmes Recording Studios: 409 (side 1), 401 (side 2).
  - Weiner, M.: With cymbals and drums, arr. by Nissimov, Nissim - Y. Fogel: Bo Dodi ("Come My Beloved"), arr. by Nissimov., 06-02-1948; 10" vinyl 78 rpm sound disc (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Paul Holmes Recording Studios: 405 (side 1), 404 (side 2). Recorded 06-02-1948.
  - Bairo - Gojouraku, 10" shellac 78 rpm sound disc (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Victor: P1219 VE, P1218 VE (matrix)
  - Engigaku - Keitoku, 10" shellac 78 rpm sound disc (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Victor: P1221 VE, P1220 VE (matrix)
  - Etenraku - Ojokiu, 10" shellac 78 rpm sound disc (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Victor: P1216 VE, P1217 VE (matrix)
  - Sazanami - Koromogae, 10" shellac 78 rpm sound disc (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 12" sound discs, 48.0 78 rpm discs (Box 2)
  12" 78 rpm test pressings, except Folder 15 which contains a commercially released 33 1/3 rpm microgroove LP disc.
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827. Sonatas, violin, piano, no. 7, op. 30, no. 2, C minor., 03-30-1938; 6 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 1-6)
    Performed by Hephzibah and Yehudi Menuhin, and recorded 3-30-1938.
    Gramophone Co. Ltd. 2EA 6177-1 [square], 2EA 6178-1 [square], 2EA 6179-1 [square], 2EA.6180-1 [square], 2EA.6182-1 [square], 2EA.6183-1 [square] (matrix nos.)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van, 1770-1827. Sonatas, violin, piano, no. 3, op. 12, no. 3, E-flat major., 3 12" shellac 78 rpm double-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 7-9)
    Performed by Hephzibah and Yehudi Menuhin.
    Matrix nos. in typescript on labels: 2AA-39-2, 2AA-40-2, 2AA-41-2, 2AA-42-1, 2AA-43-1
  - Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897. Sonatas, violin, piano, no. 1, op. 78, G major., 4 12" shellac 78 rpm sound discs: 3 double-sided discs, 1 single-sided disc (Box 2, Discs 10-13)
    Performed by Hephzibah and Yehudi Menuhin, piano and violin.
    Matrix nos. in typescript on labels: 2AA-32-1, 2AA-33-1, 2AA-34-1, 2AA-35-1, 2AA-36-1, 2AA-37-1, 2AA-38-1
  - Brahms, Johannes, 1833-1897. Hungarian dance [unspecified], 02-21-1950; 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound disc (Box 2, Disc 14)
    Performed by [Yehudi] Menuhin; T[heodore] Saidenberg, piano, and recorded 2-21-1950.
    Matrix no. handwritten on label: D9-RC-1294-1
    Separated Materials note
    Disc is slightly damaged and has been moved to a separate, specially constructed box. Contact the Head of the Archive of Recorded Sound for assistance.
  - Lalo, Edouard, 1823-1892: Concerto for violin and orchestra in F major, op. 20. Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Rondos, violin, string orchestra, D. 438, A major., 12" vinyl 33 1/3 rpm LP microgroove sound disc (Box 2, Disc 15)
    Performed by Miriam Solovieff, violin; Orchestra of the Vienna State Opera; Henry Swoboda, conductor.
    Concert Hall: CHS 1143
  - Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847. Concertos, violin, orchestra, op. 64, E minor., 12" shellac 78 rpm sound discs (Box 2, Discs 16-18)
    Performed by Y. Menuhin, Orch. des Concerts Colonne, G. Enesco, conductor.
    Gramophone Co., Ltd.: (See Folder 19 for Side 1 of this work) Side 2: 2LA.2467-1 [square] Side 3: 2LA.2468-1 [square] Side 4: 2LA.2469-1 [square] Side 5: 2LA.2470-1 [square] Side 6: 2LA.2471-1 [square] Side 7: 2LA.2472-1 [square]
  - Mendelssohn-Bartholdy, Felix, 1809-1847. Concertos, violin, orchestra, op. 64, E minor. - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Sonatas, violin, piano, K. 378, B-flat major. Andantino sostenuto e cantabile., 12" shellac 78 rpm sound disc (Box 2, Disc 19)
    Side A: Performed by Y. Menudin [i.e. Menuhin], Orch. des Concerts Colonne, G. Enesco, conductor. Side 1 (of 7 sides): Gramophone Co., Ltd. 2LA.2455-1 [square]. (See discs in Folders 16-18 for remaining sides)
    Side B: Performed by Taltah and Yehudi Menuhin. Gramophone Co., Ltd. 2EA.6621-3 [square]
  - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Concertos, violin, orchestra, K. 218, D major., 02-11-1939; 6 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 20-25)
    Performed by Fritz Kreisler and orchestra, and recorded 2-11-1939.
    Gramophone Co., Ltd. 2EA.6212-3 [square], 2EA.6213-4 [square], 2EA.6214-2 [square], 2EA.6215-3 [square], 2EA.6216-4 [square], 2EA.6217-4 [square]
  - Paganini, Nicolò, 1782-1840. Moto perpetuo. (Perpetual motion) (Allegro de concert, op. 11)., 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound disc (Box 2, Disc 26)
    Performed by Jascha Heifetz. Victrola 12835 (matrix 74581)
    Small portion of label detached and stored in separate envelope.
  - Pizzetti, Ildebrando, 1880-1968. Sonatas, violin, piano, A major., 05-06-1938; 7 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 27-33)
    Label for disc in Folder 33 detached from disc, stored in separate envelope.
    Performed by Yehudi and Hephzibah Menuhin, and recorded 5-06-1938.
    Gramophone Co., Ltd. 2EA 6610-1 [square], 2EA.6611-1 [square], 2EA.6612-1 [square], 2EA.6613-1 [square], 2EA.6614-1 [square], 2EA.6615-1 [square], 2EA.6616-1 [square]
  - Pizzetti, Ildebrando, 1880-1968. Sonatas, violin, piano, A major. Selections - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Sonatas, violin, piano, K. 301, G major. Allegro., 4 12" shellac 78 rpm double-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 34-37)
    Performed by H[ephzibah] and Y[ehudi] Menuhin.
    Gramophone Co., Ltd.: 2EA.6610 I [square], 2EA.6611 I [square], 2EA.6612, 2EA.6613, 2EA.6614, 2EA.6615, 2EA.6616
    Side B of disc in Folder 28: Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, 1756-1791. Sonatas, violin, piano, K. 301, G major. Allegro. Gramophone Co., Ltd. 2EA.6622
  - Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Sonatinas, violin, piano, D. 384, D major. Andante., 12-15-1949; 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound disc (Box 2, Disc 38)
    Performed by [Yehudi] Menuhin, and recorded 12-15-1949.
    Matrix no. handwritten on label: D9RC 2026-1
  - Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Sonatas, violin, piano, D. 574, A major., 1949-1950; 3 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 39-41)
    Performed by [Yehudi] Menuhin. Matrix nos. handwritten on labels: D9RC 2031-1 (recorded 12-08-1949), D9RC 2031-1 (recorded 12-09-1949), D9RC 2032-1C (recorded 02-02-1950)
  - Schubert, Franz, 1797-1828. Sonatas, violin, piano, D. 574, A major., 1949; 3 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 42-44)
    Performed by [Yehudi] Menuhin; A. Baller, piano, and recorded in 1949.
    Matrix nos. handwritten on label: D9-RC-2028-2A (recorded 12-2[?]-1949), D9RC-2029-2 (recorded 12-08-1949), D9RC 2029-1 (recorded 12-13-1949)
  - Wieniawski, Henri, 1835-1880. Légende., 2 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound discs (Box 2, Discs 45-46)
    Performed by Y. Menuhin and orch., Geo. Enesco, [conductor].
    P.M. Invendable: 2LA.2473-1, 2LA2474-1, 215138
  - Etenraku., 12" shellac 78 rpm double-sided sound disc (Box 2, Disc 47)
    Performed by Imperial Court Orch. of Japan. Part 1: Victor M 111 - Part 2: Victor M 112
  - Kaddish., 12" shellac 78 rpm single-sided sound disc (Box 2, Disc 48)
    Performed by Y. Menuhin.
    P.F. Invendable: 2CA-928